<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>NumFOCUS Foundation</title><link href="http://numfocus.github.io/numfocus.org/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://numfocus.github.io/numfocus.org/feeds/ralf-gommers.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://numfocus.github.io/numfocus.org/</id><updated>2014-07-01T00:00:00-05:00</updated><entry><title>John Hunter Technology Fellowship awarded</title><link href="http://numfocus.github.io/numfocus.org/news/2014/07/01/john-hunter-technology-fellowship-awarded/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-07-01T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Ralf Gommers</name></author><id>tag:numfocus.github.io,2014-07-01:numfocus.org/news/2014/07/01/john-hunter-technology-fellowship-awarded/</id><summary type="html">&lt;img alt="Olga Botvinnik" src="/media/img/fellowships/olga_botvinnik_2014fellow.jpg" style="height: 150px;" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&amp;#8217;re thrilled to announce that the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://numfocus.github.io/numfocus.org/pages/john_hunter_fellowship_2014.html"&gt;2014 John Hunter Fellowship&lt;/a&gt; has been
awarded to &lt;strong&gt;Olga Botvinnik, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UC&lt;/span&gt; San Diego&lt;/strong&gt;.  The focus of her Fellowship will
be to create open source analysis software for the single-cell and biology
communities, and to pioneer data, code sharing, and computational
reproducibility within the single-cell and &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RNA&lt;/span&gt; biology communities.  She will
take up this Fellowship in the second half of 2014, and collaborate
with her academic mentor &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://yeolab.ucsd.edu/yeolab/Home.html"&gt;Gene Yeo&lt;/a&gt; and software mentor &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://ged.msu.edu/"&gt;C. Titus Brown&lt;/a&gt;. You can
read more about &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://olgabotvinnik.com/"&gt;Olga&amp;#8217;s work at her&amp;nbsp;site.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The selection process was not an easy one - there were a number of high quality
applicants that we would have loved to be able to award a fellowship.
Honorable Mentions go to &lt;strong&gt;Damien Irving (University of Melbourne)&lt;/strong&gt;
and &lt;strong&gt;Connie Gao (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;MIT&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This first Numfocus Fellowship Program has gotten off to a promising start.
We&amp;#8217;re aiming to expand the program in the coming years to 5-10 fellowships each&amp;nbsp;year.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary></entry><entry><title>Announcing the NumFOCUS Technology Fellowship Program</title><link href="http://numfocus.github.io/numfocus.org/news/2014/03/11/announcing-the-numfocus-technology-fellowship-program/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-03-11T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Ralf Gommers</name></author><id>tag:numfocus.github.io,2014-03-11:numfocus.org/news/2014/03/11/announcing-the-numfocus-technology-fellowship-program/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;From the beginning of its founding, Numfocus has aimed at setting up a
Technology Fellowship Program. Therefore we&amp;#8217;re thrilled that this Program is
now a reality, with the first &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://numfocus.github.io/numfocus.org/pages/john_hunter_fellowship_2014.html"&gt;call for applications&lt;/a&gt; issued&amp;nbsp;today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The vision for the Program is to award 5-10 fellowships each year, with the
majority of funding coming from industry.  The dual goals of the Program are to
provide a capstone experience for talented individuals after completion or
towards the end of their PhD, while at the same time boosting open source
scientific computing projects - in line with Numfocus&amp;#8217; mission. That mission
was also guiding for selecting these topics as the ones for which applications
are particularly&amp;nbsp;encouraged:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Accessible and reproducible&amp;nbsp;computing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enabling technology for open access&amp;nbsp;publishing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Infrastructural technology supporting open-source scientific software&amp;nbsp;stacks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Core open-source projects promoted by&amp;nbsp;NumFOCUS&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A fellowship is awarded to the Fellow, it&amp;#8217;s explicitly not research funding for
his/her mentor (although we of course expect that any Fellow will prove to be
an asset for any research project(s) he&amp;#8217;s involved in). This is a deliberate
choice; while a good mentor (and host institution) is very important in order
for the fellowship to be successful, the fellow himself is more important
still. Also, the educational goals of the fellowship program require that we
weigh the potential educational value to the applicant in addition to the
quality of the applicant and of his/her&amp;nbsp;proposal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Numfocus values transparency in how it operates, and that includes disclosing
how the funding for this first fellowship was obtained. The main funder is &lt;span class="caps"&gt;JP&lt;/span&gt;
Morgan who, as we published &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://numfocus.github.io/numfocus.org/news/2013/11/08/jp-morgan-sponsors-pydata-and-women-in-technology/"&gt;before&lt;/a&gt;, committed $25k to a fellowship. Then
when we decided on a 6 month duration and looked at the income situation for
postdoctoral fellows, we decided that while $25k (= $50k/yr) is quite common
(see what &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NIH&lt;/span&gt; rates are for example), it&amp;#8217;s unacceptably low given that we want
to receive applications from strong candidates in science and engineering.
Instead $33k is a lot more reasonable. The remaining $8k of funding is taken
from Numfocus income - personal donations and the share of proceeds from the PyData
conference that PyData donates to&amp;nbsp;Numfocus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You may have noticed that we named this first fellowship in honor of John
Hunter, the late Matplotlib founder and one of the founding directors of
Numfocus. We intend to award one John Hunter Fellowship each year. Other
fellowships will likely simply be named Numfocus Technology&amp;nbsp;Fellowship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given that this is the first round of applications, we&amp;#8217;re also very interested
in any kind of feedback you may have (please send to &lt;a class="reference external" href="mailto:info&amp;#64;numfocus.org"&gt;info&amp;#64;numfocus.org&lt;/a&gt; or the
numfocus mailing list) - what information is still missing, what would have
made this call (even) more interesting for you, what elements should we
definitely keep,&amp;nbsp;etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&amp;#8217;re looking forward to receiving strong and exciting&amp;nbsp;applications!&lt;/p&gt;
</summary></entry></feed>